Guide to the Lady Sundon, Letterbook
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
[Letterbook]
1701-1800
OSBORN FC110
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1 Volume
Manuscript, in more than one hand, of a collection of about 315 copies of letters to Charlotte (Dyve) Clayton, Lady Sundon. Almost all the letters in the first volume are from Sarah Churchill, the Duchess of Marlborough, regarding the Duchess' involvement in secret political affairs and intrigues, including those surrounding the son of James II, whom the Duchess calls "the Pretender." The first volume begins with "A list of Papers the Dutchess of Marlborough gave Mrs. Clayton to read, and beg'd they might lye in her custody, which they did for twelve months not careing to trust them in any other hand, and being afraid to keep them in her own house," and "The Cypher the Dutchess of Marlborough (when she went abroad) left with Mrs. Clayton to write to her by." The second volume contains letters, dated between 1722 and 1732, by various correspondents including Mary, Countess Cowper, the Duchess of Kent, the Countess of Pomfret, and the Countess of Pembroke, and are of a primarily social nature; topics include visits in town and Mrs. Clayton's health.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
For provenance information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The following finding aid is a complete inventory of the contents of Osborn fc110. This list was reformatted from previously existing cataloging.
Ciphers; Letters; Nobility -- Great Britain; Women -- Political activity; Women authors; Great Britain -- Court and courtiers; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 1660-1714; Great Britain -- Social life and customs -- 18th century; James, Prince of Wales, 1688-1766; Marlborough, Sarah Jennings Churchill, Duchess of, 1660-1744; Sundon, Charlotte Clayton, Baroness, -1742
- OSBORN FC110
  - ANNE, QUEEN OF GT. BRIT., 1665-1714
    - Letter (copy) to Sophia, Electress of Hanover, consort of Ernest Augustus, Elector of Hanover (1630-1714), 1714 May 19 (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      St. James
      2 p.; 38 x 24 cm.
      Asks that she "contribute to the
      security of the Succession".
      110/I/91
  - ANNE, QUEEN OF GT. BRIT., 1665-1714
    - Letter (copy) to George, king of Gt. Brit. and Elector of Hanover (1660-1727), 1714 May 19 (Box 1)
      Warns him not to disrupt the
      succession.
      110/I/92
  - [ANONYMOUS]
    - 3 letters (copies) to Sarah (Jennings) Churchill, duchess of Marlborough (1660-1744), 1714 Jun 5-11 (Box 1)
      Hanover
      4 p.; 38 x 24 cm.
      Concerns the proceedings of the
      Electoral Court and the death of
      Sophia, Electress of Hanover,
      consort of Ernest Augustus, Elector
      of Hanover (1630-1714).
      110/I/94-96
  - BENSON, W.
    - Letter (copy) to Charlotte (Dyve) Clayton, Lady Sundon (d.1742) (Box 1)
      n.p.
      1 p.; 38 x 24 cm.
      Expression of gratitude.
      110/II/314
  - BURNET, GILBERT, 1690-1726
    - Letter (copy) to Charlotte (Dyve) Clayton, Lady Sundon (d.1742) (Box 1)
      Sends his sermon and a copy for
      Sarah (Jennings) Churchill, duchess
      of Marlborough (1660-1744).
      110/II/316
  - CLARKE, SAMUEL, 1675-1729
    - Letter (copy) to Charlotte (Dyve) Clayton, Lady Sundon (d.1742), 1728 Oct 15 (Box 1)
      Windsor
      Describes the health of Caroline,
      queen consort of George II
      (1683-1737).
      110/II/271
  - CLAYTON, ROBERT, BP. OF CLOGHER, 1695-1758
    - 15 letters (copies) to Charlotte (Dyve) Clayton, Lady Sundon (d.1742), 1730-32 (Box 1)
      1730 Apr 30 - 1732 Jun 25
      Dublin
      45 p.; 38 x 24 cm.
      Correspondence about books, church
      politics, and Parliament; mentions
      such figures as: John Perceval, 1st
      earl of Egmont (1683-1748), and
      Lionel Cranfield Sackville, 1st duke
      of Dorset (1688-1765).
      110/II/194-195,272-287
  - COWPER, MARY (CLAVERING), 1ST COUNTESS COWPER, 1685-1724
    - 23 letters (copies) to Charlotte (Dyve) Clayton, Lady Sundon (d.1742), [1713]-1722 (Box 1)
      [1713] - 1722 Jun 21
      various places
      26 p.; 38 x 24 cm.
      Friendly correspondence about social
      events, personal health, William
      Cowper, 1st earl Cowper (d.1723),
      Caroline, queen consort of George II
      (1683-1737), John Churchill, 1st
      duke of Marlborough (1650-1722), and
      other public figures.
      110/II/98-100,102-111,113-124
  - COWPER, WILLIAM, 1ST EARL COWPER, D. 1723
    - 2 letters (copies) to Charlotte (Dyve) Clayton, Lady Sundon (d.1742), 1713 Oct 4 (Box 1)
      Colgreen
      About the health of his wife, Mary
      (Clavering) Cowper, Countess Cowper
      (1685-1724).
      110/11/101,112
  - CRAGGS, JAMES, 1657-1721
    - Letter (copy) to Charlotte (Dyve) Clayton, Lady Sundon (d.1742), 1713 Nov 17 (Box 1)
      Directions for Sarah (Jennings)
      Churchill, duchess of Marlborough
      (1660-1744).
      110/I/3
  - DERHAM, WILLIAM, 1657-1735
    - 2 letters (copies) to Charlotte (Dyve) Clayton, Lady Sundon (d.1742), 1731 (Box 1)
      1731 Oct 12 and 1731 Dec 14
      Upminster
      3 p.; 38 x 24 cm.
      Asks Lady Sundon to intercede with
      110/II/312-313
  - GRAHAM, M.
    - 10 letters (copies) to Charlotte (Dyve) Clayton, Lady Sundon (d.1742), 1728 (Box 1)
      1728 Apr 7 - Dec 15
      Pickill
      8 p.; 38 x 24 cm.
      Asks for money and royal favors
      and positions.
      110/II/199-208
  - HOADLY, BENJAMIN, BP. OF WINCHESTER, 1676-1761
    - 40 letters (copies) to Charlotte (Dyve) Clayton, Lady Sundon (d.1742), 1715-32 (Box 1)
      1715 Aug 10 - 1732 Dec 27
      62 p.; 38 x 24 cm.
      Personal correspondence about court
      and religious politics, gossip, and
      his affection for Lady Sundon.
      110/II/125-156,191-193,196-198
  - KENT, JEMIMA (CREW) GREY, DUCHESS OF, D. 1728
    - 33 letters (copies) to Charlotte (Dyve) Clayton, Lady Sundon (d.1742), 1722-27 (Box 1)
      1722 Dec 2 - 1727 Aug 6
      Wrest House
      20 p.; 38 x 24 cm.
      Friendly correspondence about health
      the court, and social events.
      110/II/158-190
  - LEWIS, H.
    - 3 letters (copies) to Charlotte (Dyve) Clayton, Lady Sundon (d.1742), 1731-32 (Box 1)
      1731 Jul 19 - 1732 Nov 3
      Kew
      Letters of gratitude.
      110/II/209-210
  - MARLBOROUGH, SARAH CHURCHILL, DUCHESS OF, 1660-1744
    - Letter (copy) to Anne, queen of Gt. Brit. (1665-1714), n.d. (Box 1)
      Protesting her faithfulness to the
      Queen out of whose favor she has
      recently fallen.
      110/I/88
  - MARLBOROUGH, SARAH CHURCHILL, DUCHESS OF, 1660-1744
    - Letter (copy) to George I, king of Gt. Brit. (1660-1727), n.d. (Box 1)
      Denies accusation that she or her
      husband wrote a letter to James,
      Prince of Wales, the Old Pretender
      (1688-1766).
      110/I/97
  - MARLBOROUGH, SARAH CHURCHILL, DUCHESS OF, 1660-1744
    - Letter (copy) to Abigail (Hill) Masham, Lady Masham (d.1734), [ca. 1713] (Box 1)
      Scathing denunciation of Lady Masham
      at the time she became chief
      confidant to Anne, queen of Gt. Brit.
      (1665-1714); mentions Robert Harley,
      1st earl of Oxford (1661-1724).
      110/I/89
  - MARLBOROUGH, SARAH CHURCHILL, DUCHESS OF, 1660-1744
    - 86 letters (copies) to Charlotte (Dyve) Clayton, Lady Sundon (d.1742), 1713-1721 (Box 1)
      1713 Oct 15 - 1721 Jul 8
      203 p.; 38 x 24 cm.
      Personal correspondence to "my best
      friend"; subjects range from politics
      to clothes, friends to finance; most
      letters were written from Europe
      where the Marlboroughs were in exile
      in 1713-1714; letters mention: John
      Churchill, 1st duke of Marlborough
      (1650-1722); Anne, queen of Gt. Brit.
      (1665-1714); Henry Somerset, 2nd duke
      of Somerset (1683-1757); James,
      (1688-1766); Henry St. John, 1st
      viscount Bolingbroke (1678-1751)
      Abigail (Hill) Masham, Lady Masham
      (d.1734).
      110/I/ 2,4-87
  - MARTIN, E.
    - Letter (copy) to Charlotte (Dyve) Clayton, Lady Sundon (d.1742), [no yr] Sep 11 (Box 1)
      Hammersmith
      Letter of thanks.
      110/II/211
  - OXFORD, ROBERT HARLEY, 1ST EARL OF, 1661-1724
    - Letter (copy) to Sophie, Electress of Hanover, Consort of Ernest Augustus, Elector of Hanover, (1630-1714), 1714 May 30 (Box 1)
      Assures her that the Anne, queen of
      Gt. Brit. (1665-1714), favors the
      succession of her family.
      110/I/93
  - PEMBROKE, MARY (HOWE) HERBERT, COUNTESS OF, D.1749
    - 22 letters (copies) to Charlotte (Dyve) Clayton, Lady Sundon (d.1742) (Box 1)
      18 p.; 38 x 24 cm.
      Friendly correspondence concerning
      gossip about court society, health
      and weather.
      110/II/250-269
  - POMFRET, HENRIETTA LOUISA FERMOR, COUNTESS OF, D.1761
    - 37 letters (copies) to Charlotte (Dyve) Clayton, Lady Sundon (d.1742), 1725-31 (Box 1)
      1725 Jul 27 - 1731 Aug 7
      48 p.; 38 x 24 cm.
      Letters include advice, news of
      court events, expressions of
      friendship, and inquiries about each
      other's health.
      110/II/212-248
  - SUNDERLAND, ANNE (CHURCHILL) SPENCER, COUNTESS OF, 1683-1716
    - Letter (copy) to Charlotte (Dyve) Clayton, Lady Sundon (d.1742) (Box 1)
      Explains the cipher used by Sarah
      (Jennings) Churchill, duchess of
      Marlborough (1660-1744), in her
      correspondence.
      110/I/1
  - TALBOT, WILLIAM, BP. OF DURHAM, 1659?-1730
    - Letter (copy) to Charlotte (Dyve) Clayton, Lady Sundon (d.1742), 1719 Jun 24 (Box 1)
      Salisbury
      Hopes for continued good health for
      Lady Sundon and her husband.
      110/II/315
  - VOLTAIRE, FRANCOIS MARIE AROUET DE, 1694-1778
    - Letter (copy) to Charlotte (Dyve) Clayton, Lady Sundon (d.1742), 1729 Apr 18 (Box 1)
      110/II/157
  - WAINWRIGHT, J
    - 23 letters (copies) to Charlotte (Dyve) Clayton, Lady Sundon (d.1742), 1729-32 (Box 1)
      1729 Jan 17 - 1732 Dec 26
      27 p.; 38 x 24 cm.
      About politics, religion, and legal
      matters between client and lawyer
      also concerns Wainwright's attempts
      at poetry and drama; mentions Robert
      Clayton, bp. of Clogher (1695-1758),
      and Robert Walpole, 1st earl of
      Orford, 1676-1745.
      110/II/288-311